Hey, hey. What's up, my friend? So, I've
been trading for more than 10 years now.
You know, tried different strategies,
systems,
patterns, indicators, and whatnot.
And looking back
right now from today,
there are three three types of
strategies that has stood the test of
time. And if you ask me, this are the
three types of strategies likely to
continue to work in the foreseeable
future. And this is why in today's
training, I want to share with you what
these three trading strategies are. So
this is why today you will learn the
three trading strategies that I believe
will continue to work for the
foreseeable future. Mean reversion,
momentum, and trend following. I will
walk you through the concepts behind
these strategies, the characteristics of
these strategies, the pros and cons of
this strategies. Because here's the
thing, no trading strategy works all the
time. No trading strategy will profit in
all market conditions. They always have
their pros and cons to it. So I'll share
with you what they are. I'll give you
the complete trading rules of all of
these trading systems, the entries, the
exits, the risk management, so on and so
forth. And all of these trading systems,
I've back tested them, right, for 10
plus years or more. some of them even as
far back as 25 years. I'll also provide
you chart examples so you can quickly
understand these strategies and
concepts. You might be thinking but ring
you know all these strategies and
systems that you're about to teach
they're all based on back tested results
you know in the real world of trading
things are different. Yes, I get it
right. Just because something works in a
back test doesn't mean that it works in
the real world of trading, right? But I
can dare say that the strategies and
concepts that I'm about to share with
you are things that I apply to my own
live trading account. And here's the
proof. This is the results of my own
life trading account. And you can see
over here it's from 2019 to right now
2025. And over the last, you know, five,
six years, I've been consistently
beating the markets. And guess what?
This account over here is using the same
concepts, same strategies, mean
reversion, trend following, and
momentum, right, that you're about to
learn in today's training. So, I can
dare say these are the stuff that
actually do work in the real world of
trading. So, if you're ready, then let's
get started.
So in this section you will learn a mean
reversion trading system that has
generated 2834%
over the last 25 years. So let's get to
it. So what is mean reversion trading?
So I want to make sure that we are all
on the same page over here. So mean
reversion trading is when stock price
deviate from their average price because
when they do they usually revert back to
the mean. I'll show you shortly, right?
What this looks like on the chart. And
as a mean reversion trader, you look to
profit from this snapback. So, imagine
this. Imagine there's a rubber band, an
invisible rubber band in my hands. When
I pull that rubber band and I let it go,
what happens? The rubber band snaps
back. So, it's the same thing for stock
trading. So, as a mean reversion trader,
what you're trying to do is this. You're
identifying, in fact, let me just move
on to the concept first.
You're looking to identify stocks that
are in an uptrend something like this
and then you wait for a pullback and you
buy on the pullback. You're not waiting
for confirmation reversal pattern or
whatsoever. As a mean reversion trader,
mean reversion stock trader. You are
trying to catch the falling knife. Okay?
You buy on a pullback, buy when the
market looks bearish and when the market
makes a bounce, okay, you sell thereby
capturing this bounce, this quick profit
over here. So this is the goal of a mean
reversion trader someone trading in the
stock market and of course this concepts
that I've shared with you the idea it is
not enough right to develop into a
trading system because a trading system
must have a fixed set of rules when
exactly do you buy when do you sell how
much to buy and sell and stuff like that
and this is where we move on into
the trading system itself so earlier the
min reversion the concept is more of a
highle strategy so now we're moving into
the system with exact trading groups
So, we're going to be trading stocks in
the Russell 1000 index. Pretty much the
largest 10,00 stocks in US. So, you can
easily enter your trades and exit them
with minimal slippages. Time frame is a
daily time frame. And risk management,
20% of your capital for each stock and a
maximum of five positions. I want to
explain this one a little bit because I
think many traders watching this might
be thinking, man, re what does it mean?
Let me explain. So, imagine you have
$10,000 trading capital. What this means
is that you can hold a maximum of five
stocks
and each stock you will buy $2,000 worth
of stocks. So, 2,000 2,000 2,000 2,000
2,000. Okay? And if you buy five stocks,
you will realize that all your capital
will be used up. So, there's no leverage
involved. So, let's say for example,
stock, let's call it stock A, there's a
valid trading setup and you want to buy.
How much stock A do you want to buy?
Well, you buy $2,000 worth of stock A
because that's the maximum amount of
dollar value you can assign to one
stock. Make sense? Now, let's have a
look at the trading rules of this
system. So, number one, the stock is
above the 200 day moving average. So,
this is the criteria to define
an uptrend. It's kind of like, you know,
you want to make love to your wife, you
want to pop the question, you want to
hint to her when she's in a good mood.
Same for stock trading. When you want to
buy stocks, especially if you want to
make money on the long side, you want to
make sure that the overall market, the
overall stock is in an uptrend. So, the
way we do it is that the stock must be
above the 200 day moving average. Next
one, second rule, and by the way, some
of you are, you like to ask me, Raina,
should I use the simple moving average,
the waiter, the exponential?
My answer is this. It doesn't matter. It
doesn't matter whether you're going with
the SMA, the EMA, the WMA, the MMA,
whatever, because the concept is what
matters. If you think about this, the
difference between the 200 SMA, EMA,
whatever MA, the value is going to be
very minimal. Okay, maybe one could be
let's say a value of 200 for the SMA,
then the EMA, the value could be 200.5
or 201. It doesn't really going to
change much. So really, the concept is
what matters. And I would be worried or
you should be worried if someone tells
you that it makes a big difference
because if it does makes a big
difference it clearly the trading rules
are overoptimized and the strategy the
system will likely not work in the real
world of trading. So whether you go with
200 day simple moving average or
whatsoever it is not important. What's
important is the concept behind it which
is pretty much one thing to define
stocks that are in an uptrend. There are
many ways to go about it and in this
case I just simply use the 200 day
simple moving average.
Next one the stock closes below the
lower ballinger band. So this is the way
to define the pullback and again it's
not the only way you can use RSI
stoastic or whatsoever. But in this
example for this system I use the
ballinger band.
When that happens you then place a 3%
buy limit order
for the stock. So this is to help us
define stocks that are oversold and the
3% buy limit order is based on the
previous day closing price. Okay, just
to be clear over here. So number four,
if your order is filled,
you sell when the 2-day RSI crosses
above 50 or after 10 trading days. So
this is the criteria to exit your trade.
So most of the time you will exit when
the 2-day RSI crosses above 50. I would
say 80 to to 90% of the time you will
exit through this mechanism. But there
are times right when you capture a
falling knife and a stock price just
goes down day after day like diary and
it doesn't even even make a bounce. So
this is where we want to have a
timebased stop loss to cut our loss
after 10 trading days. A maximum of 10
trading days and this criteria will be
used if this doesn't happen. So there
are times right where stock price just
diary you still have to hold that stock
for 10 trading days and then sell it
right if the 2day RSI has not crossed
above 50 within the 10 days. And finally
if there are too many stocks to choose
from select the ones that have increased
the most in price over the last 150
days. So because you're trading stocks
in the Russell 1000 there's a thousand
stocks that
that that you can trade. So sometimes
there are many opportunities lined up
for you. What happens is that you'll be
spoiled for choice like a buffet. Oh,
which one do I pick? So, this is where
the ranking system comes into play. You
want to select stocks that has increased
the most in price over the last 150 days
because these are stocks that
are the strongest. That's why they went
up the most in price over the last 150
days. And these are the stocks that are
likely to continue higher. So, that's
our ranking system. And finally,
the Ballinger bands. We tweaked the
settings a little bit. We use 2.5
standard deviation instead of the
regular two standard deviation for most
uh charting platforms. When you insert
Ballinger band, it's usually 20-day
moving average and two standard
deviation. For this one, we go with 2.5
standard deviation. So in this in this
case, right, we are looking for the
stock to be or rather to define it to be
more oversold in that aspect. Now let's
have a look at an example so you can see
how this trading rules look like and
also how to add the indicators and
adjust it on your trading view platform.
So I'm using the replay mode. Let me
just see.
Okay, looks better now. So first thing
first, we need to make sure that the
stock price is above the 200 day moving
average. So you look for SMA. Click on
this. I'm just going to change this to
style. I like it black because that's
how I define my 200 day moving average.
So, we can see the stock price is above
the 200 day moving average. Our first
criteria is met. In fact, if you need a
refresher because you have a memory of a
goldfish like me. Number one, the stock
price is above the 200 day moving
average. Number two, the stock closes
below the lower Ballinger band. So, next
thing we need is the Ballinger band. So,
look for Ballinger band. If you recall
the Ballinger bands that we use, we
tweak the settings slightly. We go with
2.5 standard deviation. So you can see
over here original settings was two. So
I'm changing changing it to 2.5. Okay.
And then you re you would remember that
it has to be closed below the lower
Ballinger band. So over here you can see
over here the stock price did close
below the lower Ballinger band. So what
we need to do now is to place a 3% buy
limit order to see if we get filled on
the trade. So what we need to do is to
find out what is the closing price on
this for this candle here and then just
multiply it by 0.97. So I went to get my
calculator. So you can see the closing
price is 27.71.
You're going to multiply by 0.97
and you get 27.71
multiply by.97
26.87 87. Okay. And what I'm going to do
is just going to illustrate on the chart
where is 26.87. I'll use this green line
over here. Boom. Oh, it's red. Let me
just change this to green to signal our
entry. And according is 26.87.
Okay. So, what's going to happen is that
if the next day the stock price falls to
this green line, we would have gotten
filled on the trade because we are
placing a buy limit order with your
brokerage account. So you can see over
here, boom, next day the market
gap down lower and obviously we're going
to get filled depending on what price
you might get filled at a lower price
compared to the limit order that you've
gotten filled as well. So anyway, you
will you will be filled on this trade.
So now next thing to remember is what's
the exit? Exit is when the 2-day RSI
crosses above 50 of the 10 trading days.
So the next indicator that you will need
is clearly the RSI indicator.
relative strength index. I'm just going
to change the settings so you can see
how I do it. The length is two period.
We don't need the moving average one. So
just going to remove this and click
okay. So at this point you can see that
the RSI value is actually 0.95. We're
looking for it to be above 50. So let's
see if it goes up higher or not.
Still below right right now it's 15
13. Boom. 71. You can see so now the 2D
RSI is above 50. This is where we're
going to exit this position possibly for
for a loss.
So now as you can imagine this right the
RSI value is only confirmed
this is only confirmed when the market
close. So of course you can't exit your
trades when the markets are closed. Well
you can trade after market hours but
usually you get very poor feels. So what
we're going to do is we only exit this
trade then at the next day when the
market opens. Boom. So it opens over
here
right at this price point. In fact, if
you want I can just use this tool over
here. It changes to red.
Okay. And this is our exit. So we can
see over here we bought at this green
one and we sell at this red level. And
clearly this is going to be a losing
trade. But the purpose of this chart is
not to show you winners or let you
think, oh man, this is the holy grail.
You're going to win all the time. know
it's just to kind of like show you how
the trading setup works where we enter
where we sell and whatn not and of
course one trade doesn't mean a thing
because it could just it's just random
luck right in the short term so this is
why when you have a set of rules when
you have a fixed trading system you can
run a back test on it and see how this
system has performed over the last you
know in this case 20 over years let's
have a look okay so you can see over
here this is the equity curve of this
trading system over the last 25 years up
about 202 2,834% over the last 25 years.
Breaking breaking this down further, you
can see the month- on-mon year results
like in 2000 January is up 12%. For the
year is up 97%. 2024 the system made
29%. We have a few losing years like
here, here, here, here. So, four losing
years over the last 25 years. Not too
shabby. And for the detailed breakdown,
you can see over here
2,834% since 2000. So annual return is
about 14% a year. 66% winning rate, 33%
losing rate. Payoff ratio, this is
important. So let me explain. So how we
define payoff ratio is that we take our
average profit divide by our average
loss. And we you will realize that for
this system your payoff ratio is less
than one. So what this means is that on
average your losses are larger than your
winners. And you might be thinking so if
that's the case then how are we still
how is this system still profitable?
Well the reason why this system still
makes money in the long run despite
having the average size of the losses
being bigger than the winners is because
of this your relatively high winning
rate. You're winning about 66% of the
time. So you can see that you're winning
twice as often compared to losing,
right? You you lose 33% of the time and
you win 66% of the time and maximum draw
down is 27%. So what does this mean? So
let me explain. This is again very
important especially when you are
trading strategy systems or whatsoever.
You want to know what's the maximum draw
down of the system that you are
potentially trading. So let's say if you
have $100,000 trading capital and let's
say over the last 10 years the worst
your capital went down to was let's say
$50,000 and then eventually went back up
higher to let's say $200,000. So from
100,000 down to 50,000 we call this a
50% draw down. That's the maximum draw
down that you have experienced trading
this let's say this system right over
the last x number of years. So from the
peak to the tri we want to measure how
deep is that decline in terms of
percentages. So the deepest the maximum
decline we call that the maximum draw
down and for this system is 27%. And to
put things in perspective if you buy and
hold the S&P 500 let's say from 2000 to
right now today I believe your maximum
draw down for the S&P 500 is 55 or 60%
thereabouts. So this is to kind of kind
of like give you an idea of what's the
maximum draw down for a buy and hold
investor in the stock markets.
And
moving on the pros and cons let's talk
about the pros and cons of mean
reversion trading because no trading
system is is perfect. So I just want to
let you know what are some of the
advantages and disadvantages that you
will experience. Number one, you have a
relatively high winning rate, right?
Mean reversion trading systems. I
generally see it, you know, above 60%
winning rate. Some even as close as 70%
is doable as well. This type of trading
strategy you usually do well when the
stock market is ranging or in a choppy
bullish market because if you imagine
this, if the market is bearish, you are
not going to get too many stocks to
trade because most of them are going to
be below the 200 day moving average in a
downtrend. So, you won't have too many
trading opportunities. At the same time,
if the market is very bullish going
parabolic, you also won't have too many
opportunities because there isn't a
pullback that you can buy into because
remember this trading systems you buy on
a pullback. So if the market is very
strong going parabolic, again, this
system is likely to underperform. So
usually it does well in a choppy or
bullish but still choppy bullish market,
this system tends to do well. The
downside is you get the less than one
to1 riskreward ratio because you've seen
earlier the average loss is slightly
bigger than your average profit. And
finally, you would tend to give back
profits in a bare market or rather I
would phrase it, you would tend to not
do so well in a bar in a bare market.
And give back profits in a bare market
meaning that sometimes you could buy the
stocks and then the market goes into a
sudden fear, right? It drops like 10%,
20% like for example the recent tariffs,
right? So a number of your positions
right are going to get hit when such a
sudden decline in the stock market
happens. So you will tend to defect
profits or you'll see your account go
into a draw down during this period. And
of course it doesn't go down forever
because if you recall we have a trend
filter for the stocks. The stocks must
must be above the 200 day moving
average. So if the overall stock is in a
bare market going down 20 30 40% by then
you're probably in cash already. And for
systems like this you'll remain in cash
till things reverse and then you start
going back long to look for
opportunities again.
Now at this point you might be wondering
man right now you know how do you go
about back testing your trading
strategy. So how do you get so many
trading ideas where you have a mean
reversion strategy you have trend
following your momentum. So what so if
you're interested what you can do is go
down to my website over here
tradingwithra.com
okay and you'll be bought brought to a
page like this you'll see my face
smiling at you and what I want you to do
is to download this free guide called
the essential guide to systems trading.
Just click on this orange button, enter
your email address, and I'll send it to
your email for free. In this guide, I
will share with you the process I use to
develop new trading strategies. I will
share with you how I back test my
trading systems, the tools and resources
that I use. So, if you're interested to
learn more, to dig more, go and grab a
copy of this uh essential guide to
systems trading.
In this section, you will learn a
momentum trading system that has
generated 535%
since 2016.
So, let's get to it. So, what is
momentum trading? So, momentum trading
is a strategy that goes long on market
that have shown
the best momentum, the strongest
momentum. And the way we define momentum
is very simple. It's kind of like
imagine like acceleration. how how fast
did something move over a given time
period. So for trading we're looking at
how many percent increase did the market
did the asset price move over a given
period could be over 2 months, 6 months,
12 months etc. And the reason why we are
looking for markets that have shown
strong momentum is because
it is likely to continue higher.
So the concepts behind this strategy is
to identify markets that exhibit strong
momentum. I'll share with you shortly
how we define momentum and we're going
to hold the position till moment term
stalls or show signs of weakness. So
let's have a look at this trading
system. It's pretty pretty unique and
something that you might not have you
know come across before. So this system
we will be trading the ETFs market
exchange traded advance ETFs market and
the reason we do this is because I just
want to give you a different flavor
exposure to the different types of
trading systems out there. Can momentum
trading be applied to the stock markets?
Yes, I could go down that direction but
for this video I figured, you know,
let's let's do something different. We
we'll trade ETFs instead. And again
these ETFs are readily readily
available. You can easily find them
through this different tickers over
here. Like we are trading gold, the
ticker is GLD. We are trading S&P 500,
the ticker is SPY. Then we have TLT
which is the Treasury bond and DBC which
is the commodities market. The time
frame is monthly. How often do you come
across a trading system that trades once
per month? And the beauty about this
system is you only need 10 minutes a
month and that's it. and you will have a
system that has consistently beat the
market. So, I'll get to that shortly.
And for risk management, 50% of your
capital for each my bad, this one
shouldn't be stock. This one should be
ETFs for each ETF. And a maximum of two
positions. I think you're probably
familiar with what this means by now
because I covered that in the previous
system. If you are struggling with
struggling with what it means, then just
go back and recap. And because I'm a
little bit of OCD, I'm going to change
this right now for each ETF. Okay.
So, let's have the have a look at the
rules of this trading system. The rules
of the trading system is really simple.
As you can see over here, just three
lines over here. First one, the ETF is
above the 200 day moving average. Why do
we do this? Think about this. I'll give
you three seconds. One to three. The
reason is simple. We want to buy or go
long on markets that are in an uptrend.
So markets that are in an uptrend and
they have shown the stronger signs of
the strongest momentum, we want to buy
those markets. But first, we want to
make sure that it's in an uptrend and we
do it by making sure that it's above the
200 day moving average. Second one, for
the ETFs above the 200 day moving
average, next thing we're going to do is
to rank them according to their rate of
change. Simply put, right, we want to
rank them based on their price
performance over the last 12 months. So
let's say, let's keep it keep it simple.
So let's say 1 2 3 4. Let's say ETF 1,
ETF 2, ETF 3, ETF 4. Let's say ETF 1
over the last 12 months, it went up 1%.
ETF 2 went up 2%. ETF 3 went up 10% and
then ETF 4, let's say, dropped 5%.
Now ask yourself, which among these four
ETFs, which are the two best performing
one? Assuming that they all above the
200 day moving average. I'll give you 5
seconds. One, two, three, four, five.
Okay, the answer is this one and this
one because they has they have the
largest price increase over the last 12
months. And if you're wondering how do I
have that shown on the chart, you know,
Raina, can you show me which indicator
do I use? What is the rate of change?
Don't worry, I'll get to that really
shortly. And finally, the last one is
just to go long the top two strongest
ETFs, which is what I've just explained
shortly. I mean, previously. Okay. Now
let me walk you through how to go about
finding or rather identifying this
system right using trading view charts.
So first thing that we want to do is to
remember we are trading these four
markets gold, SMB, bonds and
commodities. So what you can do is that
if you want to trade this system you can
create
a new watch list if you want. Let's see
how do we create a new watch list. Okay,
over here I would then let's say
create a new list. Let's call this
ETFs. Okay.
And in ETFs, let's add in the four
tickers that I've shared with you
earlier. GLD is one, SPY is the other.
The other one is DBC, which is the
commodities. And we have TLT, which is
bonds. Okay, we have all four ETFs. So
now this is done on the I think I forgot
to mention on the first trading day of
each month. So right now as I'm shooting
this video, it's like the 10th of July.
So you should always do this or rather
preferably do this on the fixed trading
day of each month. And for the rules of
the system I shared with you, the back
test was done on the first trading day
of each month. So the first trading,
let's assume that you know whatever
you're seeing now is the first trading
day of each month. Okay, assume that
it's the first trading day of July. So,
how do you know which ETF to buy among
this four over here? So, if you remember
the rules,
number one is to be above the 200 day
moving average. So, let's get out get
out the popular moving average
indicator. I'll change this to 200 day
moving average.
Okay,
there you have it. Okay, so we have
number one, GLD is above it, SPY is
above it, commodities is above it and
bonds is below it. So we know that bonds
is out already. So we left three
contenders, gold, S&P 500 and commodity.
So among these three, which two should
we be buying for this month? So this is
where we need to bring out our rate of
change indicator. Just look for ROC or
rate of change. Click on this. And this
one, I'm going to change this to
12. Okay. And if you remember, this is a
monthly time frame. We're looking for
over the last 12 months, which is which
ETF has increased the most in price over
the last 12 months. This I'm just going
to change this to a monthly time frame.
And then at this point, I am going to
look at the ROC value, the rate of
change value, which is over here. So I'm
going to buy the two strongest one for
this month. So in this case, I can see
that goal is 34. Again, you can use
Excel spreadsheet or a document just to
write somewhere in case you don't
forget.
Gold is 34. Okay. You look at S&P 500,
it is 13 as shown over here. And
finally, if you look at DBC, which is
commodities, the value is -1
over here. So, this is a no-brainer,
right? So, this means that for this
month, we need to buy two ETFs, which is
gold and spy. And this is are the two
ETFs that we should be buying for this
month if you were to trade this system.
And how much of gold and spy should you
buy? Again, very simple. We are going
with 50% position size and a maximum of
two positions. So simply put, if let's
say you have $10,000,
you'll put $5,000 for this month in gold
and $5,000 in the S&P 500 for this one.
And that and that's it, right? This is
the trading system, the exact trading
rules. And this is why I said that you
can trade this system in less than 10
minutes per month. Now let's have a look
at the results of this of this trading
system and see how he has fed since
2016. Oh yeah, one thing before I get to
the results, I also need to talk about
the system.
When do you sell the system or when do
you sell the ETF? So very simple, you
only sell your ETFs
when it drop out of the ranking. So if
it stops being the, let me just go back
to the rules.
If it stop being the top two strongest
ETF, you sell it and then replace it
with the next strongest one. And of
course, you also sell it. If the ETF
goes below the 200 day moving average,
you would sell it as well. But let's say
for example gold and the S&P over the
last few months it has been very strong.
So if you trade this system you realize
that for the past I would say six months
or so there's no trades at all because
you're just consistently holding gold
and the S&P because when you keep
rolling or rather you keep
scanning or running the system each
month you realize the positions is the
same. You're still going to be holding
S&P and gold. Let's say next month come
August and you do what I've just shared
with you realize that S&P and gold is
the ones that you you should be holding
for the month as well. But if you're
already holding it then there's no
reason to sell. Just continue holding
it. And if that's the case, you probably
be done in like what less than 5 minutes
for the month. Okay. So this is a
monthly trading system. Don't forget
that. And now if you look at the rules
or rather the results, you can see this
is the equity curve of this trading
system. And if we drill it down deeper,
you can see that since 2006.
In case you're wondering why did we run
this back test since 2006 is because
some of these ETFs, they are not
available before 2006. So the earliest I
could start is 2006, which is not bad
because it's before the
2008 financial crisis. So you have the
chance to, you know, test this system on
multiple crisis like the 0809 financial
crisis, Russia, Ukraine, war, COVID,
etc. And for this system 2006 is up 15%.
2024 the most recent year up 26%. And we
have a few losing years in between like
in 2011 and this one is it is it 2015
and here as well and here as well. And
the losing years are pretty shallow if
you ask me. It's just single digit
losses. And later on I'll share with you
a a trading a trading hack a trading tip
that I think most retail traders do not
know on how you can actually reduce the
number of losing years to just a handful
right I will share with you that
technique later on. So this is the
results and if you break it down even
deeper you can see that since 2016 it's
up about 535%. Annualized basis is about
10% a year on average. Winning rate is
close to 60%. Losing rate is about 40%.
payoff ratio is 1.13. So this means that
your average winners is slightly larger
than your average losses losers and
maximum draw down is 22%. Again we
talked about what is draw down earlier.
So again go back and watch the video if
you missed this part.
And to conclude this trading system, the
pros and cons for momentum trading and
in particular this ETF trading system, I
won't say this is not a pros and cons
for momentum trading in general because
momentum trading can be applied to
stocks and clearly the pros and cons
will change accordingly. But for this
system, the ETF one that I just shared
with you, the monthly trading system,
number one is that minimal time
required. 5 to 10 minutes per month,
it's all you need to trade this system.
And in fact, I shared with you step by
step how to actually execute it earlier.
There's little correlation to the stock
market because even if the stock market
is down, it's bearish, you could still
be making money for the year as you've
seen earlier. You see the results
earlier, let's say we have 2008
financial crisis. This system is up 15%.
2020 with COVID, we are up 18%, 2022
with the Russia Ukraine war in this case
we're down 3%. So there's little
correlation to the stock market and the
reason being is that even if the stock
market
declines or is in a bare market this
system can go into safe haven assets
like bonds or gold which let's say when
the overall stock market is
underperforming other assets if they are
performing this system will switch to
those assets that are performing during
those crisis period during those
recessionary period and that's how this
system can still make money even though
the stock market the stock market is
bearish.
And the downside to this system, I I
tried to think about it that but really
the downside could be there's really
nothing much to do to do for traders.
One more action, you won't get much
action from this system. And another
thing that I added previously, but I
removed is that this system is I would
say the returns are kind of like
average. I mean, it's not like
mouthwatering. Wow. 20 30% a year. It's
about 10% a year annual returns. Pretty
average if you ask me. But again, this
is it's not 10% for all types of systems
under momentum trading because if you
apply momentum trading to the stock
markets, your returns is going to be
higher. So this why I didn't put the
returns average over here because I
didn't want you to think that momentum
trading strategy the returns are only
average. So I removed that portion out.
But for the ETF, this ETF systems,
right, I would say that yeah, this the
returns for this system is kind of
average. But you have to bear in mind,
right, even though the returns is about
10% a year, not super wow, the maximum
draw down is pretty low. Oh, it's it's
only 22%.
So, if you think about it, since 2016, I
believe the S&P 500 have much deeper
draw down than 22%.
So, again, right, we whenever we look at
returns, we always have to look at it
returns relative to the risk that comes
along with it. Okay.
Okay. So in this section you will learn
a futures trend following system that
has generated 2864%
over the last 25 years. So trend
following what is it? So this is a
trading strategy that originated from
the futures market. So this is why it's
called futures trend following and it's
used by
famous traders. You know the turtle
traders guess what they are trend
followers. market wizards like at
Sakakota
and I don't know who who else I've read
a number of them right they all are
trend followers as well so this trading
strategy has been around for a long time
and it's
proven to work and there's a good chance
it will continue working for the
foreseeable future. So this is a
strategy that allows you to write trends
across different asset classes. You can
profit in bull and bare markets because
you will go long and short and you're
trading different asset classes like
indices, bonds, currency, metal, soft
commodities, etc. So this is actually
one of the secret source. Yeah. So let
me just walk you through the concepts
behind this strategy. So number one, you
want to be trading as many markets as
possible because it increases the odds
of you capturing a trend. So earlier
I've shared with you the different types
of markets we trade and of course I
shared with you over here
are the different types of markets like
currencies itself is not one market you
can have multiple currency pairs euro
dollar pound dollar Aussie dollar blah
blah blah right maybe even 10 or more
same for metals you have gold silver
copper etc. So you can see that all
these different asset classes will give
you many
markets to trade off
and like I've said earlier we are pretty
much going to buy markets that are in an
uptrend uptrend. We go long in an
uptrend and we go short in a downtrend
and we'll write the trend till it ends.
And the reason or rather the way we
write a trend is using this thing called
TSL a trailing stop-loss. And again
later on I'll share with you the
indicators that you can use on trading
view to execute it.
So let's talk about the trend following
system that you're about to learn. So as
mentioned we are trading across
different markets. So these are the
specific markets that I've put over here
that will be
used right for the back test later back
test later on. So currencies we have
pound dollar, dollar yen, Aussie dollar,
euro dollar, dollar against the Chinese
yen. So I'm going to go through them.
You can you can read it for for
yourself. time frame is the daily time
frame and our risk management is 2%. So
what this means is that when we put on a
trade and even if the trade goes against
us, we'll lose about 2% if it hits our
trailing stop loss. It's not guaranteed
2% because we are trading on a daily
time frame and waiting we are waiting
for the candle to close. So sometimes
the loss might be a little bit more like
2.2 2.3 2.4 2.5%. It is possible but
doesn't happen often. So these are the
the parameters that I'll be using for
back test later on. Now let's have a
look at the rules of this trading
system. It's really really complicated.
So brace yourself. You ready? Let's go.
Tada. That's it. Just two lines. Yeah.
So to go long, we will simply go long
when the price closes the highest over
the last 200 days. So simply put, right,
we're looking for the highest closing
price over the last 200 days. If the
market makes the highest closing price
over the last 200 days, we go long. And
we have a 6 ATR trailing stop loss. ATR
stands for average true range. This is a
volatility based trailing stop-loss.
And to show you how this looks like on
the chart, it will look something like
this. Let's say the market goes up,
comes down, and let's say this is the
highest price point over the last let's
say this the over the last 200 days. If
the market goes up and it breaks out, we
go long. Let's call it L. and we ride
the trend till it starts to reverse and
then over here we sell thereby allowing
us to capture the meat of the move.
Let's call this m not mom but the meat
of the move. So that's the idea behind
trend following and this is a long
example. A short example is just the
inverse. We go short on the breakdown
when there's a lowest close over the
last 200 days. So something like this
closes below the lowest closing price
over the last 200 days. We go short. We
ride the trend down till it ends over
here. Let's say reverse. and we buy back
over here. So thereby allowing us to to
again capture the the meat of the move
over here. So this is in essence what
futures trend following is about.
And what about a trailing stop-loss? How
do we know when exactly to you know exit
the trade? So this is where I'm going to
walk you through a few examples so you
can see this in action. Now let's have a
look at some examples shall we? So the
first one is a trading setup on coffee.
Okay. and couple of indicators that you
will find it useful. Let me show you the
first one. The first one over here you
can see is the donen channel. But this
one is actually modified to plot the
closing price. So where do you find
this? I actually developed this one
myself using a using an AI. So just look
for dungeon channel and this one is
called uh you can should be able to find
this one bracket closing price. So
that's the one I'm using. Okay. And it
looks something like this. the settings
over here. Just change this to 200 and
you should have something that looks
something like this. So if I just they
should be quite donen channel closing.
Let's see what pops up. Oh, there you
have it. Right. Wow. My name here.
Anyway, yeah. So this is the one. Okay.
So I'm just going to remove the extra
one. There you have it. So feel free to
use that.
And
next thing is Okay. So you look at it at
this point. You can see that this market
coffee we're waiting for a setup and
entry trigger to go long. So when the
price touches this blue line, so this
blue line over here demarket or
highlights the highest closing price
over the last 200 days. So if it closes
into this blue line over here, it's an
entry trigger to go long. So what
happened next is kaput. There we have
it. This candle the market has closed
right is now at this point is now closed
the highest over the last 200 days. And
since now it can only be confirmed after
the market has closed, you can't trade
after the close unless you want to do
after market hours. Don't recommend
that. Wait for the next trading day to
open and then you trade it.
So put right next day market open over
here and that's where you go long
right this opening price you go long.
Now the question is how do you then
trail your stop loss? So this is where
the second indicator comes into play.
This is a chandelier exit.
Okay. Okay. So, if you want to look for
it, I think you can just go to trading
view.
I believe I use this one from this one
over chandelier exit. Yeah, this is the
one I used. Yeah, they have it. Looks
similar. I'll remove the duplicate. And
the settings are is over here. 6 ATR and
20 period. Click okay. And there you
have it. You have this green line that
pops up at the bottom. So, what you're
going to do is to trail your stop loss.
So, when there when this market closes,
let's say suddenly reverse and closes
below this green line, okay? you exit
the trade because your trailing stop
loss is hit. It has hit 68 ATR trailing
stop loss. So in this case, let me just
fast forward.
Okay, so I I this one I have to be
honest. I cherry picked this chart to
show you how it's like riding a trend.
Looks easy on the chart, but remember
this is a daily time frame. You have to
endure all this app and flow of the
market, you know. You can see it breaks
out, it makes a pullback almost hitting
your stop loss. you still got to hold
this trade, you know, and then
eventually breaks out higher, makes
another pullback, heads up higher
again, almost hitting your trading stop
loss and then go.
So that's the the nature of trend
following. There's a lot of uh
battle of your emotions if you ask me,
especially those of you who are new to
trading. This is a strategy that again
not most new traders is able to handle
honestly speaking. Okay, then you can
see over here. Let's see when it when
does it break below the trailing over
here. Finally, on this candle over here,
the market breaks and close below your
trailing stop loss, which is over here.
And since the market is closed, you
can't exit. So, your earliest exit will
be on this candle over here at this
opening price. This is where you sell
this position for a nice profit. Okay,
so this is how the futures trend
following system look like. So, and
there you have it, right? This is the
idea behind futures trend following. And
now since our rules are objective, we
can look at the results over the last 25
years. So you can see over here this is
the equity curve I shared with you
earlier and month on month, year on
year. This is where it's important. Have
a look. So you can see that as a trend
follower, you're not going to make money
every month or every year. I think same
goes for all trading strategies. Nothing
works all the time. But what's
remarkable about trend following in
particular futures trend following is
that during a crisis period during a
recession when the stock market is
taking a beating this strategy usually
does well. You can see in 2000 we have
the dotcom bubble up 22%. 2008 financial
crisis up 65% for this system. 2020 we
have COVID up 8%. Not not huge. 2022
Russia Ukraine war up 25 or rather 56%.
So you can see that this is a system
that thrives during difficult market
environment.
And if you look at the
matrix
total return 2864 since 2000 so
annualized basis is about 14% annual
return. Your winning rate is about 45%.
You can see that it's less than half. So
you're actually losing more than half
the time or rather you're losing more
than half the time. Yeah, correct.
You're losing 54% of the time to be
exact. your payoff ratio is 1.74. So you
can see that on average your gains are
larger
pretty large right relative to your
average losses and your maximum draw
down in this system is pretty steep 37%
and it's not out of the norm right to
see draw down exceeding 40 50 or even
60%. So they are trend following hedge
funds they have maximum draw down of you
know in excess of 50% and that's really
the cost of being a trend follower. The
draw downs are not fun to go through.
It's painful. It will test your
emotions. It will test your resilience.
In fact, let me just go back to let's
see all I have all this data exported on
Excel. So, you can see over here there's
all this data exported. You can see that
as a trend follower, there are periods
where you just have to kind of like suck
it up, right? You can see over here
since over here made a new high and then
kind of like you know draw down for the
next few years over here. Same thing for
this made a new high over here and then
you have to go for draw down for a few
years. It might look short on this chart
but this like a few years it's not like
few weeks or few months. So as a trend
follower your winning rate is low as
well as you know you have to be able to
endure this lengthy draw downs.
So pros and cons of future trend
following is futures trend following is
number one there is no correlation to
the stock market. So this is a good
thing for those of you who are let's say
stock investors, stock traders, you want
a system or strategy that is
diversified. Futures trend following is
something worth considering because
later on I'll explain you know why this
is the case. This usually does well in a
bare market as you've seen earlier. The
downside to this is that this system
this strategy has a low winning rate.
Generally trend followers winning rate
are between 30 to 45% and it's difficult
for most traders psychology especially
if this is the only trading system that
you trade. It's really going to test
your your heart and soul. Okay. So, but
that's it. There are things that you can
do to kind of alleviate this this pain
especially if you have multiple trading
systems or if let's say you are long the
stock market. You could be an investor,
a growth investor, value investor. If
the stock market is bullish, your stock
investments are likely to make money and
trend following. Maybe the period
doesn't make or do it that well. Doesn't
matter. At least your stock investments
or stock trading is, you know, providing
cushion for it. At the same time, when
markets are bad, when your stock
investment portfolio take a hit, guess
what? Trend following will shine. And so
this means that your losses from your
stock investment will not be as painful
because you have trend following. Make
sense?
Next up, let's talk about the holy grail
of trading because this is something
that I believe 90% of retail traders
have never been exposed to before. When
when I realized this concept many years
ago, it really it blew my mind. So, I
want to share this with you. It's really
powerful stuff. Okay. So, the holy grail
of trading is this. It's possible to
actually reduce your risk and improve
your returns by combining multiple
trading systems. You will improve your
risk adjusted returns. So what does risk
adjusted returns means? So let's say
there are two strategies, strategy A and
B. Let's say the annual return. Strategy
A is 10%. B is also 10%. And the maximum
draw down of strategy A okay let's say
is 20%. But strategy B the maximum draw
down is only 10%. So if you look at this
these two strategies, most traders will
say, "Oh, right. They're the same, man.
We both have similar annual returns, 10%
only." But no, strategy B is a superior
strategy because it has a better risk
adjusted returns.
Both earn 10% but strategy B has lower
risk because the maximum draw down in
this case is only 10%. So this is one
way we can
look at at our risk adjusted returns. At
the same time, let's say both strategies
have similar risk. Let's say strategy A
and strategy B let's say in this case
their
maximum draw down let's say for strategy
A is 20%. Strategy B the maximum draw
down is also 20%. Strategy A let's say
in this case it has a 20% annual return
but for strategy B it has a 40% annual
return. So in this case strategy B is a
superior strategy as well because for
the same level of risk strategy B can
give you higher returns. So this is what
we mean by improving your risk adjusted
returns. So let me just show you this
table and you'll see what I mean. So if
you look at this right over here I have
two trading systems over here. The mean
reversion and the momentum. Basically
the two systems I shared with you
earlier. And on its own both of these
systems have losing years. Mean
reversion loss in money in 2014 2019
20162. Same for the momentum also has
four losing years here here and here.
But what happens when you don't trade
any of this system in isolation but
trade both of them. Let's say you have a
50/50 allocation to both of these
trading system. So let's say you have
$10,000. You allocate 5,000 to the mean
reversion trading and 5,000 to the
momentum trading system. What will
happen if you look at it the performance
over the last
from here to here? You can see that
you have made money almost every year
and just one losing year a minuscule
2.4% in 2022.
So can you see how powerful this is? The
concept of having multiple trading
systems and that's the reason why I
myself I trade multiple trading systems
because I want to utilize the holy grail
of trading to improve my risk adjusted
returns. And it's possible when you have
multiple trading systems you can make a
profit almost every year whether it's a
bull market, a bare market or even
during a recession.
Okay, before we sum up today's video,
you probably have questions for me and
these are some of the frequently asked
questions that I I get from traders.
Number one, how much capital do I need
to get started with systems trading? So,
I've shared with you three of the
trading systems here today. And for the
momentum trading system, for the mean
reversion trading system, I believe you
can get started with as little as, you
know, three or $4,000 and still have
proper risk management. For the trend
following system, that one requires more
capital if you can trade CFDs or
forwards, then you could get started
with, I would say, $20,000 for the trend
following system. And if that's too much
for you, then you can always, you know,
stick with the mean reversion and the
momentum trading system that I've shared
with you earlier. Number two, what's the
difference between momentum trading and
trend following? I get it, right? These
two concepts, they're actually quite
similar and I agree. But let's break
this down and maybe shed some light on
the difference between the two in
particular the
two systems that I've shared with you
earlier. So number one for momentum is
that we go long only. We don't go short.
Whereas the trend following system that
I shared with you, we go both long and
short. For momentum, we exit our trades
when momentum stall or when it starts to
weaken. Whereas for trend following, we
only exit the trade when it hits our
trailing stop-loss. So this means for a
momentum trading system, the trend could
still be intact. Okay?
and you would you could possibly still
exit the trade because momentum is is
stalling even though the trend is still
intact. So that's the difference again
between momentum trading and trend
following is the exits that we spoke
about is different.
Next one. What about
this one? For mean reversion trading,
isn't it dangerous to trade without a
stop loss? Or maybe even momentum
trading, isn't it dangerous to trade
without a stop-loss? So here's the
thing. Both of these trading systems, we
are not using leverage. So if you think
about this for the mean reversion
trading for the account to let's say go
to zero you need to pick five stocks
from the Russell 1000 and the Russell
1000 are the largest
the top 10,000 largest stocks in the US
and what are the odds of you picking
five of these stocks which are in an
uptrend on and all five going to zero
I've been trading mean reversion for a
number of years now and I don't even
have one stock you know going to zero.
Yeah, you can experience you know stock
declining 30 40 50% decline but going to
zero and all five going to zero it has
never happened to me and based on our
back testing over the last 25 years
never happened as well. So the odds are
pretty slim that you know you will bust
your account trading this system and at
the same time even though you don't have
a stop loss meaning a stop-loss in the
traditional sense the price based
stop-loss remember you have this thing
called a time a timebased stop loss
because we hold a trade of a maximum of
10 trading days for the mean reversion
trading and if the stock doesn't hit our
exit criteria which is the 2-day RSI
above 50 we will still exit the trade so
yes we don't have a price based stop
loss But we have a timebased stop-loss.
So we still have exit plans.
Next one. Can these strategies be
applied to other markets? So what I've
shared with you over here, I can't say
for sure how it's going to perform on
the other markets. Like for example,
mean reversion trading. How does it
perform in the forex market? Well, I
have no idea. I've not tested it before.
So this comes down to again doing the
work, right? As a trader, as a systems
trader, you have to take the ideas, the
concepts and test it to different
markets and find your ages out there
because there's a good chance there's a
possibility that one concepts that work
in a particular market could also work
in other markets. But you never know for
sure. So you have to test it and of
course
I have seen many times that just because
one system or strategy work in one
market doesn't mean it's going to work
in other markets. So this is why you
have to test test test. It's so
important. And finally, right, where can
I learn more about systems trading? So,
I believe I I spoke about this earlier.
So, if you want to learn more about
systems trading, highly recommend you go
down over here, tradingwithra.com, which
is uh yep, my website. Yep, I'm
shameless over here. And grab a copy of
this book called the essential guide to
systems trading. It is free. Okay. Okay.
And this guide is really where we will
talk more about systems trading, the
tools and resources that a systems
trader would use, what back testing
software to to use, where to get your
data, and if you do not know how to
code, how can you go about doing it? And
I also share with you my own process to
always get new trading ideas and
strategies for new systems to test on.
So get grab a copy of this guide. It's
free. And yeah, that's pretty much it,
right? So with that's it. I've come to
the end of today's training. A bit uh
longer than usual, but hopefully you
found it useful. If you do, smash the
thumbs up button, subscribe to the
channel, and I'll talk to you soon.